I need to start by telling you about the
British Rail sandwich. Two slices of
white bread, a layer of creamed butter,
and a choice of nine different fillings.
Jump on a train in 1971 and you could
tuck into any of these [music] with the
equivalent of about £2.18 in today's
money, all while traveling the length of
the country on a now classic InterCity
125. [music]
Far from being embraced as a bargain bit
of grub, however, the British Rail
sandwich gained a pretty rotten
reputation. Some people have even
complained about British Rail food,
saying it's not absolutely tip-top
value. Well, I mean, look at this.
That's a load of rubbish. The exact
criticisms varied. Sometimes they were
said to be too stale, sometimes too
soggy. The details didn't really matter
because, more than anything, the British
Rail sandwich was political. Arguably
the second most important sandwich in
British political history. And we are
saying [music]
the Conservatives are the largest party.
See, from the 1940s to the 1990s,
British Rail was among the UK's most
visible state-owned industries. For
those who wanted to see such industries
privatized, the supposedly bland British
[music] Rail sandwich became a searing
symbol of exactly the kind of bland
society which, they argued, a country
built around state-managed industries
produced. Dynamism and correct sandwich
moistness would only be possible with
the free market. When the Conservatives
eventually privatized British Rail in
the 1990s, [music] Tory MP Andrew
Robathan celebrated the end of an era of
leaves on the track,
inefficiency, late trains, restrictive
practices, but, first and foremost, old
dog-eared sandwiches. It would be a
reach to suggest that some slightly
lackluster rolls were the only thing
which brought an end to Britain's first
experiment with publicly owned [music]
rail. And yet, the aftertaste of the
British Rail sandwich long lingered
around the industry. As recently as this
January, Reform Party MP Richard Tice
demonstrated his razor-sharp grasp of
popular culture by describing some of
his political enemies as being like a
soggy, stale sandwich from the old
British Rail, an organization which at
this point hadn't existed for just shy
of three decades. [music]
That's about to change. In November
2024, the UK government passed the
[music] Passenger Railway Services
Public Ownership Act, which began the
process of bringing significant chunks
of the UK's [music] rail network back
into public ownership. The new
organization will have a slightly
different name, Great British Railways,
[music] and yet, just as British Rail
did before it, it will see rail services
in the UK run by a state-owned company.
In today's video, we're going to speak
with an economist, an engineer, a
historian, and the UK's [music] rail
minister to see whether Great British
Railways can avoid some of the PR
pitfalls of its predecessor [music]
and steer ahead into a future of
publicly-owned rail.
Or diesel ahead, I guess.
Cuz that's that's diesel.
Then I was the chair of Network Rail for
9 years, and it's from that job that I
came here, but I've been in this
industry
>> [music]
>> literally all my working life.
>> This is Lord Hendy. Lord Hendy is the
Minister of Rail in the UK's Department
for Transport. I was asked uh it was a
great privilege to be asked to be uh
minister in this government. Uh and I
believe the reason I've been asked is
because uh I've got a whole career
background in transport, and the
government's program for rail reform is
a very big issue. I arranged to come up
to London to grill Lord Hendy on why the
government feels [music] the UK's rail
network needs such a radical
intervention, and what he and his
colleagues are hoping to achieve with
these plans. You said there there that
this is like the biggest reform that the
rail network has gone through for for 30
years, and
>> [music]
>> I guess from an outside perspective,
that would suggest that maybe the
government feels that uh not
everything's going particularly
swimmingly maybe with with not perfectly
at least with the rail network. Absol-
absolutely right. And and and and I'm
passionate about it because I chaired
Network Rail for nine nine years. And
what I saw as the chair of Network Rail
was a
>> [music]
>> with was an industry where many many
people in it were struggling to make it
as good as they [music] could in
circumstances where
incentives are misaligned
the
some of the commercial deals that had
been done previously got in the way and
the result was that passengers and
freight customers for that matter didn't
get the service they they they deserved.
See, in recent years Britain's railway
network has found itself in pretty dire
straits. In February [music] 2024 the
polling company Ipsos did a bunch of
research into what people's perceptions
of the railway network are and the
results were not fantastic. Just 19% of
respondents said that they thought
Britain's railways offered good value
for money to passengers.
>> [music]
>> 22% thought they could be relied on and
as few as 20% felt that they were well
run. Worse still, a mere 16% of people
had any hope that things would get any
better over the next 12 months.
Expensive, unreliable, badly run. That
is the general impression which has come
to haunt train travel here in the UK.
Does that kind of like perception
matter? Yeah, it does. It matters I
think it matters hugely. I can still
hear announcements when I sit on
stations saying, "Oh well, your train's
delayed because of a Network Rail
infrastructure fault." People don't care
who's fault it is. What I want to know
is that somebody's trying to fix it.
>> Looking at some of these problems, I
guess there are all kinds of routes you
could have gone
Fun pun, sorry. There are all kinds of
routes you could have gone down in terms
of seeking to fix some of those
challenges and why why renationalize it?
Why is renationalization kind of become
front and center to that?
>> So, look, the Labour Party he committed
to public ownership. The really
important thing is that one set of
people, one chief executive, one set of
management, one board are going to be
large very, very largely responsible for
everything that goes on. So, there's
nowhere to hide. It might not be
perfect, it probably never will be, but
they should feel every moment of every
day that it's their job to make this as
good as it [music] can be. If the
general public agree with Lord Hendy
that the rail network isn't in great
shape, they also agree with his
solution. Polling has consistently found
support for renationalization to be over
50%.
>> For a government which does like a good
U-turn, rail reform is also something
that they've really kept on track with.
At time of recording, four so-called
train operating companies which run rail
services in Britain have already been
nationalized. They join four others
which were already being run by the
government before these recent reforms
came through because the private
companies which were supposed to be
running them either fell into financial
difficulties or performed so poorly the
government stepped in to take them over.
Sometimes it was both. The crucial
question though is will it work? And in
order to find out why, we first need to
go back to the 1990s to explore why the
railway network was privatized in the
first place and find out how things went
quite so badly
off the rails.
>> [music]
[music]
>> There's a John's hat which actually fits
>> [laughter]
>> ridiculously well. Okay, so between 1948
and 1994, [music]
every part of Britain's rail industry
was run by British Rail. And I mean
everything. I'm talking stations, track,
freight, passenger services, all of it
happened under one roof. It must be said
I wrote a book called British Rail, a
new history, which looked at the history
of British Rail over the space of its
50-year existence. And while there were
some bumpy periods, particularly at the
beginning, at the end, the last 10
years, British Rail was a very
effective, efficient organization.
>> This is Christian Wolmar. Christian is
the author of several excellent books on
the history of rail in the UK, including
2022's British Rail a new history. I
covered rail privatization
30 years ago, and I'm now covering the
[music] un-
tangling of rail privatization 30 years
on. Christian explained to me what the
rationale was for privatizing Britain's
railways in the first place. Well, it
was a fairly shambolic process because
the Tories slipped it into the 1992
manifesto on the expectation they
weren't going to win the election, but
then surprisingly they got a majority of
21 or something, which is enough for
them to
really govern through the the five
years. Now, this is far from the first
time we've talked about privatization on
this channel. Privatizations private
privatization private private private
private private privatizations private
privatization privatized privatization
privatization of privatization
privatized And most modern British
privatizations were conducted by the
same person. Thatcher Thatcher's
Thatcher Margaret Thatcher Thatcher
Thatcher's Which makes rail
privatization a little bit different.
See, Margaret Thatcher did opt to sell
off Britain's gas, telecommunications,
water, electricity, and aerospace
industries among plenty of other stuff
during her time in office. The railway,
however, was one of a handful of
state-owned industries that she decided
to leave largely alone. In 1990,
however, Thatcher was replaced by this
guy, John Major. Major was seen as a bit
of a lame duck. When the time came to
face an election in 1992, even he
expected to lose to Neil Kinnock's
Labour Party. When Major included a
pledge to privatize British Rail in the
party's manifesto then, he wasn't too
stressed about the details. Come
election day, Major snatched a slim
majority, which meant that suddenly he
did need to be stressed about the
details. They then scrambled around
Whitehall, kind of, you know, trying to
work out exactly what we're going to do.
And I really think there was a man with
a notebook who was kind of going around
various bits of
government trying to kind of work out
what to do. There were three main
options for what form a privatized rail
industry could have taken. The most
straightforward option was to float the
whole of British Rail on the stock
exchange as one massive company. Nice
and simple. The second was to divide the
company up into four, with each new
company taking charge of a different
part of the country. And this would have
reset the industry to the form it had
taken immediately prior to
nationalization back in 1948. In many
respects, that would have been a lot
better idea, but it wouldn't have then
meant that there was competition
between
the different operators, you know, on
the same tracks. And that was their kind
of nirvana. Maintaining either one
national company or several regional
ones would ensure that each of those
companies continued to have a monopoly
over the routes they ran. [music] As
such, Major decided to take a
sledgehammer to the whole industry.
British Rail was broken [music] apart
and sold off as over a hundred different
companies, with each having control of a
different part of the sector. Okay,
let's do this. So, the actual rails and
most of the stations, they were all sold
to a company called Railtrack. The
day-to-day maintenance of those rails,
however, was handed over to a different
set of companies, kind of maintenance
companies. This chap, I think, is
actually meant to be a firefighter, but
uh he's already got his own PPE, so uh
let's uh re-recruit him uh for for some
rail maintenance instead.
Freight services, they were meant to be
split up between six separate companies
which then compete for different uh
kinds of business. But, a bunch of rapid
mergers around the time of privatization
meant they ended up in the hands of just
two companies. Yeah, you for
competition. Where things got really
wild, however, was with regard to
passenger services. Kind of trains that
you or I might get. The physical trains
themselves, they were sold to a bunch of
companies which came to be known as
rolling stock companies, or ROSCOs,
which essentially operated like car hire
companies. The actual operation of a
service, say like the 9:25 from Penzance
to Truro, those were taken over by what
came to be known as train operating
companies, or TOCs.
This chap, uh he's actually a police
officer who with a gun, um but he's
going to
use his life more usefully and become a
train conductor instead.
The new business model was that the
train operating companies would bid to
the government for permission to run a
bunch of services, usually in the same
geographical area. Once they had that
permission, they would then hire the
trains themselves from the ROSCOs. If
nothing else, a fantastic time to be a
graphic designer. Uh just
just so many logos needed designing.
There was some logic behind all of this.
The government realized that generating
competition at the stage of buying
tickets was quite difficult. People tend
to need to get a particular train, or
they don't. The hope then was that
carving the industry up into dozens of
pieces would mean competition would
emerge elsewhere, as ROSCOs could bid
for train hire fees, or maintenance
companies negotiated prices on their
contracts. The result, however, was an
industry which was kind of a mess. The
creation of 25 franchises of about a
dozen engineering companies of rail
track which was
separate from the train operations,
various regulators. I mean about 100
companies kind of emerged from it. So,
it was
a very kind of
hastily put together plan
without really a clear idea. If we
wanted to point to an apparent success
of privatization, it was an increasing
how much the network was used.
Throughout the course of the 20th
century, Brits had largely been
abandoning trains as cars became more
and more affordable. Post privatization,
however, this began to change. An
increase in the frequency of services
contributed to a rapid increase in the
number of people getting the train to
the point there were more train journeys
being made each year than at any other
point since the Second World War. Now,
the big success which
privatized supporters point to is that
there was a big increase in the number
of
people using the railways.
But to my mind, that was, you know,
largely what I'd call extraneous
factors.
You know, that they were they were not
to do with the brilliant performance of
the rail companies, but rather were to
do with
the fact that the economy is growing,
people wanted to to
use
live near railway stations and that was
a big boom. Where privatization failed,
however, it really failed. I feel like
it's a fairly widely held opinion that
privatization hasn't been or hadn't been
a roaring success. [music] Um, can you
maybe speak a little bit to some of the
ways in which you don't think it worked
out so well? Well, uh the first one was
security and safety, actually, because
uh there was a series of crashes, which
I wrote about in my book Broken Rails.
Uh a series of four major crashes at at
Southall, Ladbroke Grove, Hatfield, and
Potters Bar, all of which happened
within the first four five years of
privatization,
and all of which uh can be
uh ascribed to the way that the railway
was broken [music] up so hastily, and
various kind of responsibilities
uh towards safety were were not kind of
uh properly allocated to uh any
particular companies. Railtrack, the
company which had come to own the
infrastructure aspects of the network,
lasted less than a decade before a
series of fatal crashes prompted the
government to bring it back into public
ownership as Network Rail. The biggest
impact for most passengers today,
however, has come in both cost and
quality of service. As with all
privatizations, the broad promise was
that selling off the railway would lead
to more competition and thus to lower
fares. This hasn't happened. By 2018,
the cost of rail travel, adjusted for
inflation, had increased by more than
20%.
This was in spite of government
subsidies to the industry having
tripled. Given the cost pressures that
the railway industry was costing more to
operate, they were never going to kind
of reduce the the the prices
um
or even actually keep them stable. They
they actually kept on increasing it at
some point that
fares were going up by,
you know, RPI plus 1%. The system
wherein the train operating companies
would bid to the government for
permission to run a group of services
didn't actually involve all that much
competition beyond the initial bidding
stage. This potentially incentivized a
system wherein the train operating
companies would sometimes put together
somewhat optimistic bids for how
efficiently or well they could run the
group of services, and then if the
numbers turned out not to quite add up,
to sometimes simply walk away and let
the government pick up the pieces. This
reached pretty extreme levels during the
COVID-19 pandemic when the government
was forced to step in to provide
billions of pounds in support to [music]
keep rail companies in the black. Where
privatized companies were supposed to be
taking on the risk of running services
then, the fact that the rail network is
just so important means they're
effectively too big to fail. There are
then quite specific failings which
privatization has [music] led to, but
there's also a much broader sense of
chaos and decline. Here in the country
which invented the steam-powered
railway, the sheer bizarreness and
inefficiency of this chaotic privatized
system has led to a feeling that the
railways can't work, which means Lord
Hendy and his pals in Parliament have a
pretty big task ahead of them. Let's
start by exploring one of the most
direct ways in which most people
experience some of the present
shortcomings of our current rail
industry.
Tickets and pricing.
But, to do that
we're going to need to head to a train
station.
Like
like a real a real one.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Sort of stolen valor around here.
If there's anything that anyone in the
UK will want to tell you about using our
rail network, it's that catching a train
can be eye-wateringly expensive. In
December 2024, the European campaign
group Transport and Environment
published a report which revealed UK
rail prices to be amongst the highest in
Europe. Prices on Avanti West Coast
trains were, it said, 1.5 times the
average European fare, while GWR was
charging 2.5 times the average European
fare. If you look at a bunch of
different countries, whether it's um Um,
quite high density countries like
Belgium or Japan or lower-density
countries like Denmark, Italy.
Basically, that same result obtains. Um,
you've got the UK is usually about two
or three two three four times as
expensive um as as all of those peer
countries. This is Chris Hayes. Chris is
the chief economist at Commonwealth, a
progressive think tank which has done a
bunch of work recently on how the
privatization of public services like
transport can drive up prices. Whether
it's intercity, like suburban, regional,
fast speed, all of those, the UK is
really at the top of the pack.
>> If you've watched any of my videos
before, then you might have spotted that
I live in Plymouth in Southwest England,
which is mostly served by GWR. The train
from here to London takes about 3 hours
and 15 minutes, depending on how often
it stops, or about 4 hours and 25
minutes in the car. It's also one of the
most beautiful train journeys in the
country. Take into account all the
environmental benefits, and the train
should be an easy win. In my fairly old
and therefore probably quite
fuel-inefficient car, that journey will
probably cost me in the region of 43
quid in fuel. By train, a standard class
ticket bought on the day can cost as
much as 149 pounds 50. Heck, for 130
quid, I can fly with a cabin bag from
Newquay, which is a good chunk further
away in Cornwall. Now, the really
important caveat to this is that that
149 pounds 50 ticket is for a ticket
bought on the day during peak times. And
if any of the management from any of the
remaining train operating companies or
from the government were here, what they
would probably want me to say is that
you can find cheaper tickets if you know
how. For example, if I choose to travel
at off-peak time, which is either after
9:00 a.m. or 9:30 a.m., depending on
where you're traveling from, the price
drops to a slightly more tenable 104
pounds. If I travel slap-bang in the
middle of the day, I can likely grab a
super off-peak ticket, which will bring
things down even further to £74.90.
And then there's rail cards. If I were a
bit younger or much older or traveling
with a friend or a veteran, I might be
able to save money using one of nine
nationally available discount cards or
one of these several local equivalents.
These mostly allow you to get a third
off the price of any ticket as long as
you travel either after 9:30 a.m. or
10:00 a.m. depending on where you are.
Also, on some rail cards you can
sometimes travel before 10:00 a.m. as
long as your fare costs over a certain
amount.
And let's not forget about advance
tickets. The majority of train tickets
in the UK are bookable up to 12 weeks in
advance, often with even greater
discounts if you travel at awkward
times. The limitation here is that you
are committed to a certain service and
can't get a refund should your plans
change. Also, sometimes it's cheaper to
do what's called split ticketing and buy
your tickets for your journey in two
separate parts. So, yeah, you can find
cheaper fares. The problem is that it
involves navigating a maddeningly
complex train ticketing system, which
feels like something off Nathan for You.
I implemented a strict dress code
requiring customers to wear formal
attire just to enter the store. I then
had all the dollar TVs moved to an area
at the back of the store and had a new
wall constructed [music] to surround
this area that could only be entered
through a tiny 2-ft tall door. There'll
usually be someone who pushes back by
saying, "Oh, but if you really shop
around, if you
uh look enough in advance and you find
the right sign, um you can make some
good deals if all of those conditions
are satisfied and if you have like
perfect flexibility over when um
when you need to move and like uh when
you need to travel and
uh
how far in advance you know that you
need to travel." Throughout the rollout
of renationalization project, the
government has been cautious not to
promise that the change in ownership
will definitely lead to cheaper ticket
prices. Do you think rail fares will be
cheaper? Under public ownership, we've
got to make sure that we've got enough
money to provide the services that
people want.
>> However, last November the announcement
came that the DfT would be freezing
prices on train tickets in England until
at least March 2027. This never happened
once under privatization, with prices
not only consistently rising, but
consistently rising above the rate of
inflation. While this will no doubt come
as good news to many passengers, far
less has been said about the obscenely
complicated state of pricing. The
difficulty with the peak season is
people don't travel in the peak because
they want to, they travel in the peak
because they've got to, because they've
got to be somewhere in order in order to
be at work.
>> If cutting ticket prices can at least
partly pay for itself through
encouraging more passengers, then that
seems like a win-win, particularly if
there are other cost savings involved in
removing shareholders from the equation.
The challenge is that in many parts of
the country more passengers might
actually be a bad thing.
>> [music]
>> Oh.
Let me show you a video. This is a
problem that many passengers face every
day on the trains, commuters and
long-distance travelers.
>> This is Jeremy Corbyn, former leader of
the Labour Party, sat on the floor of
the 11:00 a.m. train from London King's
Cross to Newcastle on the 11th of
August, 2016. The furore which follows
the release of this clip consumed the
British media for more than a week. A
row brewing over claims made by Jeremy
Corbyn that a train service he used
between London and Newcastle was
ram-packed.
>> When it came across the desk of Richard
Branson, whose Virgin Trains was running
the route at the time, he decided to
tweet CCTV pictures of empty seats in an
effort to debunk the claim that the
train was busy. The Corbyn team then
tried to rebut the rebuttal. It was a
whole thing. I was planning on joking
here that the coverage was a bit like a
true crime documentary. A minute later,
he passed empty but reserved seats in
coach F. And then I discovered this
actual AI generated true crime style
podcast about the incident.
>> Buckle up because we're diving deep into
train gate. Train gate. It really
captures that whirlwind of political
maneuvering and public perception. To
understand it fully, you really need to
remember the context.
>> Never before have I felt like the
machines are coming for my job so
specifically. Likely a big part of the
reason that this incident touched a
nerve with Branson and then went on to
capture the attention of news audiences
is that overcrowding on British trains
is a big issue. There there certainly is
some overcrowding. The overcrowding in
peak times [music] is less than it was.
There is also though overcrowding on
long long distance services and that's
[music] why that's one of the reasons we
need to change how the fares work.
>> A study published last year found that
on a typical day passengers were forced
to stand on more than a third of
services during peak hours. In London
more than a quarter of all passengers
during peak times traveled standing up.
So persistent is this issue and so
passionate do people feel about it that
train overcrowding in the United Kingdom
has its own dedicated Wikipedia page.
Overcrowding on trains is bad enough in
and [music] of itself. But the anger
which passengers often feel about
overcrowding is inseparable from the
anger that people feel about prices. In
fact, anger about one often fuels anger
about another. People feel pissed off
that not only are they paying through
the nose for a ticket, there's also a
reasonable chance that they might not
even get a seat. And standing on the
train, particularly trains which aren't
designed for standing, it really sucks.
And yet the inconvenient truth for
British rail passengers [music] is that
your ticket isn't expensive in spite of
the fact that you're standing, it's kind
of expensive because you're standing.
>> It all comes right back to very basic
principles of supply and demand. If a
lot of people want to buy or do a thing,
the price of that thing tends to rise.
And train travel is really really
popular in Britain. Of course, the fact
that train fares are set by government
here in the UK means the government
could opt to keep prices low anyway. The
government doesn't have to turn a profit
after all. The problems with that are
twofold. The first is that the UK rail
industry isn't particularly flush with
cash, even with some of the savings
associated with not having to pay
dividends to shareholders, which will
accompany renationalization, the
industry still receives a hefty subsidy,
not least in the form of funding to
build new lines like the Elizabeth line
in London or HS2. Government subsidy
counts for about half of the whole
[music]
uh industry's income.
>> High fares and complicated ticketing
then are the current method which the
industry uses to incentivize people to
travel at less busy times. [music]
If you wanted to be able to tackle both
overcrowding and ticket price inflation,
[music] then you would have to increase
the number of seats which are available
to buy. And if the government currently
[music] seems a little bit hesitant
about the prospect of doing that, it's
because adding more seats is actually a
bunch more complicated than it might
first sound.
Right, here we go again. Uh but first,
let me announce a real rail engineer.
Oh, come on. Like a like announce. So,
you like like a train announcement.
Thank you. We have one of the most
reliable railway systems in Europe in
terms of reliability. At the same time,
when things go wrong because of how
intensively we use our railway asset,
how how many trains we run on our track,
those delays instantly cause chaos
across the whole network. So, a small
delay can result in enormous um problems
right the way across the network. This
is Gareth Dennis, a rail engineer and
commentator who has also written a book
called How the Rails Will Fix the
Future. You cannot separate out the
ticketing system from the actual
infrastructure and the the trains and
the capacity itself. So, because our
railway system is so limited on
capacity, essentially, fares can be as
high as they need you know as they can
be as extortionately high as they are
because people are already if the trains
are full, then clearly they are able to
afford to pay those high someone is
paying those high fares. He suggested
that the challenges surrounding both
high ticket prices and overcrowding are
really just knock-on effects of
constraints surrounding what train
experts call capacity. Very simply, when
I talk about capacity, what I mean is
how many seats there are per hour going
in any direction.
>> So, if you're Lord Hendy or anyone else
at the top of Great British Railways,
and you want to increase the number of
train seats available to buy, then you
have two main options. You can have
extremely long trains with loads of
seats and they don't run quite so
frequently.
>> The first option is simply to increase
the number of carriages on each service.
And there are times when this is a
possible option. CrossCountry, the TOC
which operates some of the longest
routes in the country, is notorious for
running services with just four
carriages where there is often the
demand and certainly the ability to run
much longer trains. And yet in many
cases, this isn't quite as simple of a
fix as it sounds. One of the many
downsides of the post-privatization
system in which ROSCOs own the trains
and rent them to TOCs, is that train
operating companies generally don't have
loads of spare carriages lying around
that they can suddenly add to a service
which they think might be particularly
busy. There's no real incentive to pay
to be hiring extra carriages that you
might not actually use. In many cases,
however, adding more carriages is a dead
end.
A train can only be as long as the
platforms at which it needs to stop.
There have been efforts to extend
platform lengths where necessary and
possible, but you kind of have to stop
somewhere or you end up with a nation
that is just one long train platform. Or
you can have shorter trains with fewer
seats, but they run really frequently.
Once you've reached the limit with the
number of carriages you can fit on each
train, then your other option is to
introduce more services running more
often. And this comes with a bunch of
side benefits, too. A more regular
service isn't only better because it has
more seats, it also means that anyone
who misses their train doesn't have to
wait as long for the next one. It also
allows you to operate a greater variety
of trains. You can run an express train
which only stops at major cities and a
stopping service which stops everywhere.
Separating out long journeys and short
ones in this way is simply better for
everyone. And yet, just as you can't
have infinite carriages, you also can't
run infinite trains. And this is
particularly true on Britain's rail
network. The challenge we have in
Britain is that our urban centers, so
our big city centers, are ridden with
bottlenecks, key big bottlenecks. See,
the UK's rail network is old. Really
old. And what this means much of it is
gorgeous, it also means we're trying to
make a 21st century rail network out of
one designed for the 19th century. It is
very pretty, though. One of the key
roadblocks is that there are plenty of
portions of the UK rail network which
consist of just two tracks, one going
one way and one going the other. Even
with an infinite budget available for
trains, this massively decreases the
options available when designing your
timetable.
>> Manchester Piccadilly in the Castlefield
corridor is a a famous one in in in the
north of England where much of the
western, you know, the whole that whole
side of the country relies on that pinch
point.
>> Say you want to run one super fast
intercity service going the length of
the country carrying holiday makers and
long-distance travelers. As that passes
through somewhere like Manchester, a big
city, it's going to pass through a bunch
of different metro stations which it's
not going to stop at, it's just going to
breeze through without [music] a care in
the world. Then, following along behind
that, you can have a little metro
station which will stop at all of those
little places carrying people doing
local travel, going to work or to do
their shopping. Um and so far so good,
right? This is good. These people aren't
held up and these people get to go to
all the local places that they want to
go to. The problem comes when you want
to run another high-speed train behind
that one because this train is now just
stuck behind our little metro train. Add
on the fact that most rail lines in the
UK also have freight trains trying to
use them as well and you end up with the
mother of all traffic jams. Meanwhile in
Europe, you saw a situation where
long-distance services were being
essentially
create turned to their own separate
segregated system whether whether
high-speed or not. So, these were two
separate systems that where they shared
tracks usually had the benefit of lots
and lots of spare tracks to run on so
they weren't in conflict with each
other. The solution then is to expand
out. Building out to four or even more
tracks suddenly gives you the ability to
run different kinds of trains on
different tracks at different speeds.
Of course, if train travel is reasonably
popular here in the UK and making it
cheaper and more reliable involves
upgrading certain parts of the network,
then surely building out in this way
must be really popular. Surely the
government is keen to steam ahead with
such upgrades.
I guess it's time to talk about HS2.
What we're announcing today is where the
new stations will be for the high-speed
[music]
rail link which will go all the way up
from the south of the country all the
way to the north.
>> This is Nick Clegg who at the time he's
speaking here was the UK's Deputy
[music] Prime Minister. He's talking to
the BBC as part of the announcement of
the route for HS2 or High Speed 2. A
huge infrastructure project which as
he's just said was planned to run from
London in southeast England to
Manchester and Leeds in the north of
England. The project was enormous. It
was to involve laying hundreds of miles
of new track at cost of 33 billion
pounds. Just an absolutely massive
project all round.
>> HS2 essentially gave us a new in-city
railway system that overlaid the
existing railway. So, it sat over the
top of it, largely separated from it,
and gave cities back their railway
network.
>> There was a tension at the heart of
Clegg's announcement. As this Guardian
article from the time suggests, some
officials within the Department for
Transport were keen to avoid focusing
too much of the announcement on reduced
journey times. The key problem which the
project was designed to address was
capacity limitations, particularly on
the West Coast Main Line, which runs
from London through Liverpool to
Scotland. At the same time, this is what
the promo video looks like. [music]
>> With up to 36 high-speed trains running
on the network every hour,
it'll put 2/3 of the population of
northern England
within 2 hours of central London. Very
quickly, the whole debate around HS2
came to be almost entirely about journey
times. This proved difficult to get
voters truly excited by. When you hear
that the new line is going to shave 28
minutes off a journey from Birmingham to
London, the tendency is perhaps to think
of that as a one-off, and to perceive it
as not very impressive. We perhaps don't
immediately consider the fact that
shaving 28 minutes off a journey which
tens of thousands of people make each
day actually means saving thousands of
combined person hours every single day.
A focus on journey times also allowed
opponents of the project to massage the
figures in such a way as to make them
sound even less impressive. The Stop HS2
campaign, for example, preferred to use
a figure of 20 minutes, based on
comparing the improved journey to the
very fastest current journeys, rather
than the average current journeys. The
case for HS2 being boiled down to this
whole journey times, you know, 10
minutes, 30 minutes, 15 minutes quicker
to XYZ, came from the fact that
unfortunately that business case is the
thing that was then briefed to the
advisers, that was then briefed to the
ministers to talk to the public about.
From and it's a sequence of people who
had no understanding of the actual wider
strategy for building a railway.
>> There were also a lot of people opposed
to this project. HS2 managed to assemble
an unholy alliance of opponents from all
points on the political compass. The
first to emerge were the old school
Tories in the English shires who felt
the new route would be an eyesore. Then,
perhaps more sympathetically, came the
residents and farmers whose homes and
land were bought under compulsory
purchase powers to make way for the
route. There were also the likes of UKIP
and the Reform Party for whom investing
in high-speed public transport
presumably sounded a bit too European.
The most thoughtful opposition perhaps
came from The Sun newspaper, which
opposed the new line for being woke.
Anger on the right, however, was
accompanied by regular shunts from
environmental groups. Prior to 2024, the
Green Party of England and Wales was
officially opposed to the idea, citing
both the high cost and local
environmental impacts. Civil
disobedience group Extinction Rebellion
also opposed the project for similar
reasons. Christian Wolmar, who we spoke
to earlier, has also been a
long-standing opponent. Friends of the
Earth described it as costly and
damaging, and one group called Stand for
the Trees even made a heart-rending
campaign ad featuring Emma Thompson.
Over [music] 100 ancient woodlands are
set to be destroyed by HS2.
Don't let [music] this be their last
Christmas.
It's time to stand for the trees. Part
of the the reason that we saw this
groundswell of opposition from an
environmental perspective is that the
opposition, when it was just a policy,
started in right-wing think tanks, and
some of those had a kind of a little see
conservative bent, and so picked up some
of the discussion about environmental
impact. Then, quite easy to palate for
some of the kind of the well-off
landowner types, and people with large
homes living along the route of the
railway. That then kind of alongside a
groundswell in overall environmental
activism through the likes of uh of of
Extinction Rebellion,
allowed some of that language to get
picked up by much more radical
pro-environment people,
and sort of allowed some of those
talking points to be transferred across
from like the the right to the left, if
you like, and and sort of the strange
sort of bedfellows. On a purely
political level, then, HS2 quickly found
itself pulling up hill. They couldn't
even rely on the support of the kinds of
environmental groups who, in any other
context, you would imagine would
probably support a project with the
potential to get cars off the road and
planes out the sky. The issue, of
course, and potential impacts on nature
were also ones which tended to
exacerbate one another. Efforts to
mitigate the impact on animals or
woodlands, even when good and necessary,
cost money, which made the price tag
look even more foreboding. As things
stand, the project is planned to cost in
excess of 100 billion pounds.
Oh, and did I mention we're not even
building the whole thing anymore?
>> Substantial amounts of it got canned
off, and the most important bits were
canceled. So, yeah, very frustrating
that that story was just a a complete
failure of national storytelling there.
In 2021, Conservative Transport
Secretary Grant Shapps announced the
cancellation of the planned eastern leg
of the line up to Leeds and Sheffield.
Then, in 2022, a plan to connect the new
HS2 line to the existing West Coast Main
Line in Golborne to allow high-speed
trains to continue on to Scotland was
scrapped as well. Finally, in 2023,
Rishi Sunak took advantage of his
lame-duck period as Prime Minister to
cancel the entirety of the project past
Birmingham. Sunak argued that the money
could be better spent improving existing
lines in the north. In doing so, he was
trading off a popular narrative at the
time that HS2 mostly benefited London
and people who were seeking to get to
and from the capital, with little
benefit for people living and working
within each region. All of this
overlooks the fact that HS2 was never
really about journey times to and from
London at all. It was first and foremost
about capacity. The whole HS2 project
was really about giving high-speed
trains their own separate tracks, which
yes, would benefit long-distance
travelers, but would also allow more and
better local services, too. By taking
the hub-to-hub long-distance services
away, that then frees up the existing
network to act as it's best as, which is
a suburban network with freight running
around on it. And then you can get a
nice high-speed interconnect that goes
between all the major city center hubs.
[music]
So, that gives you a massive increase in
capacity, potentially four or five, six
times the number of seats per hour per
direction on any given line than you you
have currently.
>> Any potential that nationalization might
lead to huge upgrades in the network
then is going to exist under the shadow
of HS2. The irony of all of this is that
the UK has very recently had a similar
rail project which both opened late and
was more expensive than planned. It took
mere weeks in 2022 [music]
for the Elizabeth line in London to go
from a  and  nightmare to
the backbone of travel into and out of
the capital for many commuters. Whatever
disruption it might have caused in the
building, it's verifiably led to new
jobs and housing with 90% of passengers
saying it's changed their area for the
better. Nevertheless, pushing through
new improvements to the network
continues to be controversial regardless
of how necessary they are. And that's
something which nationalization is
unlikely to change. And yet, [music]
there is another aspect of the rail
industry which contributes to high
ticket prices and which the government
possibly could have done something about
and yet [music] is choosing not to.
Train nerds, don't worry. It's time to
talk about the rolling stock companies.
When people look for answers as to why
train fares in the UK feel so expensive,
they usually tend to assume that it's
the train operating companies that are
eating up all the cash. The reality,
however, is that the likes of Great
Western Railway or Avanti are usually
operating on quite thin profit margins.
Since 2020, the TOCs have had a deal
with the government where they retain a
set profit margin of around 2% each
year, which is extremely low when
compared with other industries. If we
want to trace where the money's really
going, we have to look at the rolling
stock companies. So, these are the
companies that own the carriages and
then lease them out
to the operators.
>> As I've already mentioned, British Rail
industry was privatized in such a way
that one set of companies, which came to
be known as the rolling stock companies,
ended up owning the physical trains
themselves and then hiring those trains
out to another set of companies, the
train operating companies. And the idea
here was that the ROSCOs would end up
having to compete for competition in
order to win contracts from the TOCs.
The whole rationale for privatization,
it would make
the service the sector more it would
ensure better quality,
greater efficiencies, and it would
incentivize investment. And the way in
which we would do that is not, you know,
it's not by magic that just having a
different owner would do it. It's
because market competition basically
sort of compels you
to to um
um do do well by the customer
um cuz otherwise your competitors will
eat your lunch.
>> created three new private companies who
were sold these trains, Angel,
Porterbrook, and Eversholt. And by all
accounts, they were given a pretty good
deal on British Rail's existing rolling
stock.
>> British Rail publicly owned trains that
we had scrimped and saved for over
decades and a pretty new fleet in the
early '90s
given away for trivial amounts of money
to and in fact, what's interesting is
the amount that the the valuation of
that rolling stock was done by the same
people who then bought the rolling stock
afterwards.
>> The broad intention was to kind of
create car hire companies but for the
railway network. The reality, however,
to borrow a phrase from Gareth, was that
we ended up creating train landlords.
One problem is that different bits of
track often require quite specific
trains. So, for the diesel stuff, you
can do it on most of the network. For a
lot of the electrified
um
stock,
uh it depends on the type of um
type of electrification, whether it's
overhead line, whether it's third rail
stock.
>> The so-called Javelin trains, which run
from London St. Pancras into Kent, for
example, have to be able to run on
overhead electric wires while traveling
along the High Speed 1 line to Ashford,
and then switch to take power from a
third rail electric line for onward
journeys into Kent. If you're the TOC
operating that line, you can't just
decide to hire a different train
instead. You need those very specific
capabilities. Similarly, if you need a
tilting train to enable you to maintain
high speeds along the West Coast Main
Line, you're going to need to rent a
Pendolino. The amount of latitude for
haggling that you have is actually
pretty weak, which can give the ROSCOs
the ability to simply railroad TOCs
during negotiations. Rolling stock
companies got a lot of this stuff on the
these assets on the cheap. They They
then started massively overcharging. Um
this is very This has been very well
documented. People started noticing it
pretty soon after um
after privatization. Even the regulators
started to realize that competition
didn't um happen.
>> As of the last rail industry finance
statistics released by the Office of
Rail and Road, ROSCOs were claiming an
annual 19% profit margin. They had also
paid out 275 million pounds in dividends
to shareholders just that year. In fact,
in the period since 2018, during which
the rail industry has had to navigate
the COVID-19 pandemic and recovery, the
owners of the rolling stock companies
have managed to walk away with 1.8
billion pounds in dividends. What makes
this worse is that the era of
privatization has seen the amount of
government subsidy going to the railway
industry increase, meaning that those
profits and shareholder dividends aren't
only coming from expensive fares, but
also more or less directly from
government coffers. So actually, um,
the Roscos, even while they weren't
directly receiving any any subsidy,
[music]
they were receiving a great deal of
indirect subsidy that was being
channeled through the uh the operating
companies. Talking about rail
nationalization over the past few years,
it's been tempting to talk about how
Britain is nationalizing its trains. The
reality, however, is that the physical
trains themselves are remaining in
private hands. As is the ability to
charge through the nose for their use.
>> Those companies who have
have invested, you know, tens of
millions of pounds in rolling stock,
there's not much point in the government
buying that out when actually the
service they're providing in terms of
the leases of the rolling stock that
they're putting into the network, uh uh
uh
are largely very adequate. We will get
better value out of it because with GBR,
we can guarantee a much longer life of
contract than they than they ever they
could with franchises with relatively
short terms. We just want the best best
for the customer and the taxpayer.
So if they offer us a good deal for
future rolling stock, we'll take it. And
if they don't, we'll do something
different, won't we? It's certainly the
case that nationalization might open up
new models for ordering and funding new
rolling stock. The trains for HS2, for
example, will be owned directly by HS2
Limited, the publicly backed company
building the line. It's also possible
that the government's new-found monopoly
over running services might allow it to
negotiate better deals. With over 80% of
Britain's trains still owned by the
rolling stock companies, however, that
outflow of cash from the industry to
shareholders is likely to continue for
the foreseeable future. And all of that
contributes to the need for high ticket
prices and government subsidy.
Nevertheless, bringing the rest of the
rail industry together under one roof
isn't completely pointless.
That's a pun because uh switches, where
do you like swap from one track to
another, are sometimes referred to uh as
points, I think.
I'm like I'm I'm not an expert. My track
is made from wood.
>> Let me show you one last video. Since
the new timetable came in
what, nearly 2 weeks ago,
I've been late to work every single day.
>> In May 2018, a new timetable was
introduced for train journeys in the
north and parts of the southeast of
England. The changes were meant to be
exciting, seeing the implementation of
various technical upgrades which had
been made to the network in each region
over the previous few years. In the end,
it was an absolute disaster. The brand
new timetable and we didn't have enough
drivers, enough trains, or enough tracks
to run the timetable and the consequence
of that was that it completely fell over
in several parts of the country
resulting in
complete travel chaos for millions of
people. Over the next few weeks, over
13,000 train services were cancelled
across the country. The transport hubs
of Manchester and Hull were hit
especially bad, along with many commuter
towns around London. During certain peak
times, nearly 2/3 of all train journeys
didn't even leave the first station. So,
essentially the collapse of the previous
system of operating passenger trains in
the UK. The key problem was a lack of
drivers. Both of the train operating
companies which were the worst affected
technically had enough drivers, but they
hadn't had the necessary training on the
correct rolling stock and routes to
allow them to run the required services.
[music]
The new timetable also ended up being
drawn up later than would usually be
expected giving everyone less time to
adapt. Underlying all of these specific
problems, however, was the core issue of
industry fragmentation.
>> We've spoken a lot in this video about
the decoupling of rolling stock
companies and train operating companies.
But, the manner in which the train
industry was fragmented during
privatization has led to all kinds of
absolutely bizarre examples of friction
and added expense. Because they broke up
a coherent
integrated business into lots of
different companies. Each of those
companies had to have relations with
other companies, and therefore they had
to have lawyers, and they had to have
human resources departments, and they
had to have managing directors,
>> [music]
>> and they had to, you know, find ways of
allocating risk and and so on.
>> Tomorrow morning, there should there'll
be a meeting between operating
engineering people all over Britain,
[music] various meetings, looking at
what happened yesterday. I want that
meeting to concentrate on making sure it
doesn't happen tomorrow. I don't want it
to worry about whose fault it was and
how who where the money goes to as a
consequence, because what we've learned
over 30 years of the railway is that
people just get used to that. It's a
it's a blame game. It it doesn't solve
problems in the way that it should. In
drawing up plans for Great British
Railways, the government have talked a
lot about the new organization as
creating a single directing mind for the
industry. Bringing maintenance of the
track and stations back together with
the running of services should, in
theory, mean everyone is pulling in the
same direction. That's a much better way
of organizing things than me having a
contract to repair the track and you
having a contract to run the trains and
us, or the people who work for us, going
off into a corner and having [music] a
big row about whose fault yesterday's
delay was, and more importantly, who
should pay for it. There is, in theory,
also a decent amount of money to be
saved here. The Department for Transport
has expressed that it expects to save
around 100 million pounds in management
fees. What I want people to do is to
work together for to produce the best
service they can. And that's not just
altruistic. Actually, the railway will
do better if it's more reliable. We know
that what happens is you generate more
passengers. That improves revenue. That
will reduce that will that will reduce
the cost to the taxpayer, which is
actually massive following COVID.
And in the end, it will produce
something better for the country, better
for the country's economy, better for
society and and better for jobs, growth
and and homes. At the same time it's
freezing prices. It's also looking to
cut back on the amount of subsidy the
industry receives. Essentially the
railways are you know the railway is a
system from an engineering perspective
it is a system and in a way we're kind
of undoing some of the last 30 years
where we kind of pretended it wasn't a
system and split it all off. Stitching
it back together.
>> I'm reluctant to try and promise
extraordinary benefits out of this
[music] in terms of much cheaper fares
cuz the reality is the treasury have
putting billions into the railway more
than pre-COVID because the number of
people traveling to work is less than it
was. But what I'm absolutely convinced
we can do is to make it fairer, make it
easier to pay, make it more transparent
about what you'll about what you can do
to get
to get cheap tickets and and prices that
are affordable in a way that people will
trust [music] the railway more.
Nationalization isn't going to magically
fix all of the railway industry's
problems. What it is however is a signal
that public transport is important.
[music] Too important to be left up to
the often short-term whims of private
companies. What it does more than
anything is puts [music] rail transport
back on the ballot paper meaning that
even if you don't think that this
particular government does a fantastic
job of running the railways you kind of
get the option to vote for another one.
If you want to see Britain's railway
network stretched to its limits then you
need to go over and check out the recent
season of Jetlag The Game which turns
the UK's rail network into a massive
board game. If you live in the UK you
can also feel extremely jealous as the
team speed around on unlimited travel
tickets they only sell to tourists.
Jetlag is a Nebula original series and
it's just one of an incredible range of
original shows available on the
platform. You've probably heard of
Nebula by now. It's the premium
streaming service created by myself and
a bunch of other thoughtful creators.
If, like me, you're a massive fan of the
video essays of Lindsay Ellis, for
example, and have been feeling her
absence on YouTube, you'll be very
excited to know that she is still
releasing stuff pretty regularly over on
Nebula, [music] much of which is
completely exclusive to the platform. I
recently really enjoyed her dive into
the rise of body cam YouTube, exploring
the ethics of this strange new evolution
of the true crime genre. Lindsay's work
is just a sliver of an ever-growing
catalog of exclusive films and shows
available to watch only on Nebula. But,
joining the platform also allows you to
watch all of my regular videos from both
this main channel and my second channel
ad and sponsor-free. If you use my link
go.nebula.tv/tomnicholas,
>> [music]
>> you can get 50% off an annual plan,
which brings the price down to just
£2.50 per month or whatever your local
equivalent is. That's far, far cheaper
than any other streaming platform out
there, and there are also no uplifts for
4K or no ads or whatever they're trying
to get away with now, either. Or, if you
don't want to add another monthly
payment to your budget, you can sign up
for a lifetime subscription. This costs
more up front, and yeah, it grants you
access to Nebula for as long as both you
and the platform exist. Signing up to
Nebula really does help us support my
work. It allows us to come and interview
important people and do a little bit of
traveling to make the stuff even better.
Not only do we get paid more every time
you watch our stuff over on Nebula, but
we also get a little bit of a kickback
uh whenever you sign up using my link.
That link again is
go.nebula.tv/tomnicholas.
Thank you so, so much for watching once
again, and I'll see you over on Nebula.
All that's left for me to do is to say a
massive thank you to the people who
support my work over on Patreon. Uh
those people over on the top tier are
Richard Garry, Dickon Spain, Bill
Mitchell, Sedcee Reese, Zoe Olden,
Alexander Blank, Niels Zebulon Gard,
Sophia R, Sergio Suarez, Richard Rapone,
Gabriel Coke, Fiasco Linguini, Agent
Maxwell, Glenn Sugden, Emil, Jarabar,
Yilmazson, Publius Idicus, Sam
Fortunato, Sondre Yassen Gene, Douglas
Urquhart, Ahmed Harajic, and Hasty. If
you want to join them in getting a
little insights into what I'm working on
at any point, a couple of the scripts to
my videos, and a bunch of other stuff,
you can find out how to do so at
patreon.com/tomnicholas.
Thank you so much for watching once
again, and I'll see you in the next
video.